Hello. So, first I want to say thanks for
the organizers to provide such a
beautiful venue so that we can here to
present to all of you.
So, my name is Mark Hung. I come from Taiwan.
I'm a LibreOffice developer and in last few years I worked a lot in Writer and Impress
issues mainly related to CJK languages,
So today I'm going to talk about to
review some of the issues I have faced
and some stories behind them.
so it's not quite it's not a very technical talk but just share some of my stories.
So, in LibreOffice, there are many features that are designed
specifically for CJK users such as Asian
typography that we are allowed to use
hanging punctuation and like we have line
breaking rules that we can state
forbidden characters at the beginning of
the line and end of line,
and Asian kerning and character compression for
punctuation and kana, Japanese kana.
Also, we have justify alignment rules.
Japanese and Chinese users have different justify rule compared to other languages.
And also some contexts we write a vertically
or filling special form of paper called "case grid paper" that is "gǎozhǐ" or "genkou youshi."
So, and also, we use Ruby or Asian phonetic guide to mark ideographs
so they are the reader the readers know to pronounce an ideograph.
And, we have other language tools like conversion tools for simplified Chinese and traditional Chinese,
and also, there is the conversion tool for Hangul and Hangcha for Korean people.
So, and also, there are some features that
are not visible from the user interface
but we need them every day such as
support of input method, or mixing
Western and Asian script,
or like support of characters like some special characters like Ideograph Variance sequence,
and Unicode characters that are
not in Basic Multilingual Plane.
So, these features designed specifically for CJK users, so the other way that it is hard
for other language users especially for
Western people to understand how they
should be used or what the expectation
of the those the behavior of those
features so sometimes it get very long
to get a back fist.
Okay, so how did everything begin.
So I just want to share about my story that how I began to have LibreOffice.
So, back to 2014,
I worked an organisation with roughly 600 computer
computers and 400 people and I my
department was responsible for the
office suite migration and I I was
working I worked on promoting promoting
at that time we have deployed OpenOffice
and so I was I worked on promote or
improved migration of the office suite
so there are a few typical questions from end-users.
For example, that where
we were from time time we face the
question like why do Chinese numbers in
the number list, numbering list in my
in my DOCX or DOC, or RTF, those
Microsoft format files, become Arabic numbers,
and why our country Asian punctuation marks so close to the text behind,
and why do punctuation marks go outside the printing area, and why our text ill-formatted.
So, we developed a kind of
answers to those questions for example
we have to teach users how to create
number list, list style, and then apply
it and ask them to save it to Open Document
Format otherwise if they reload the same
file they will find that the format this
was missing again.
so that's kind it's nothing wrong to
save to Open Document Format I think that
is the right thing to do. But, on the
other hand, it becomes quite a burden
because creating number list style is kind
of more advanced in my point of view.
So, and for other questions like those text formatting issues, I I will ask them to turn off the CJK features
such as character compression like pen punctuation or text grid, so at that time
the CJK features we can cut some time a road block behind us.
So, I, how, then...
there is something done my colleague
told me he said that if you've got a
simplified Chinese document then the
numbers the numbers the Chinese numbers
in the document will show up correctly
so that's a very strange clue to me
because this you can display simplified
Chinese in the number list in the
Microsoft Office format
why couldn't display the traditional
Chinese ones because for the lower
number is one two three four five six
seven those are totally the same.
so it's kind of knowledgeful and in my opinion I think it must be very very easy to fix this kind of issue.
So, in the summer I think it's when I was going to leave the office and I was very worried or
frustrated
working on a document and then I thought
why why should why shouldn't why not is
try to look into what inside the
document so I just unzip the document, so
if you know, that those documents are
actually zipped, zipped file for many xml
files, and those xml files are all the
text text format that you can read with
any kind of text reader.
Then I start looking for some interesting keyword
inside the document,
so, then, there is something I remember I don't exactly
remember if it is taiwaneseCountingThousand
or chineseCountingThousand,
but anyway there because they are pure
text, I can easily recognize that this
is something I want to looking for.
So, I googled the keyword, and I search
the source, and then I try to make a
patch, and then I submit a patch to
Apache OpenOffice. I think it's in the August 2014.
However, that, while, I'm,
after waiting for my patch to review for three months.
I decide to try to submit
my catch to LibreOffice gerrit,
and to my surprise, my patch get reviewed in one
day and then it gets merged by the way
Miklos reviewed my, my patch and then in
several days my patch just get merged.
So I told that, I told my colleague about
this, then we are excited about this.
So we switched to LibreOffice in next year.
So, because of this, I think because regard
of this problem very often in our document
they are always number list, after this fix
in these the burden of the support largely reduced.
So, after that,
I become, I became a regular contributor.
So, I started with number list, then all kind
of than the number list in different
kind of file formats, and then related issues
such as underline, character, any keyword that
that is related to that, then I started
to try if I can fix those problem is
take document that I can found in my
office space, and then later I just look
at started to look at the CJK issue list,
so it will expand the area of my interest, so, and so on.
So this look has some of interesting CJK issues
so at that time as I mentioned that the user this is one of the frequently as user questions that
why the text behind the punctuation mark go close to the previous one.
So, is there anyone
who want to guess the reason?
Okay, so this is a specific issue for
traditional Chinese users that for
character compression that worse by
pulling the text behind the punctuation
for those punctuation marks like voice
comma, full-width dot, full-width period.
So, they put text behind.
So why can you do that?
Because, in Japanese, the comma and period are designed close to the
previous text,
so if you put behind a one third of one first, then it's you will not affect the result of for mention, but
for Chinese especially in traditional
Chinese users, our punctuation marks are
around the center of the grid, so when
you simply believe through the text to
front to the front then you will find
together like this.
so it take me some time to understand that there... when we say CJK features sometimes they're
actually designed after the Japanese
formatting rules.
So I feel it's quite interesting.
So, like similar things happened
while I fix the hanging punctuation issue.
So, like, there is... so... like... we can see in
my text example, hanging punctuation is very
far away from the water, so, because that
the Japanese design text layout rules
that you have your punctuation marks are
more close to to the previous text so so
it seems more obvious to traditional
Chinese users, but anyway, I just try to
find out everything I can found on the CJK issue this, so... so, now makes it
makes the solution of the text more
consistent when there is hanging punctuation.
And then, after I... after I try to look at
the CJK META issue, then I started
doing something now I didn't use myself
like this one. That's Ruby.
So, I thought that, I just think, maybe this will be
useful for Japanese people and they will
feel inconvenient without them, so so now
that ruby support in DOCX or DOC
format are more robust now.
And then, and,
we try I try to look at some strange
issues like when there are strange
characters the justifying alignment will
show and show up ill... ill-formatted and
like aligns extrude the the if you there
is underlined or or cross lines, they
will issue the area of the of the page.
And also, try to make borderlines
and underlines more consistent.
So... so, as I mentioned in the earlier slide
that when.. when in 2014,
there are few typical questions and they
are one of them that about my... my... my
document just look ill-formatted, and the
our advice is just turn off the text
grid in the page style. So... so, this... that
is because that there is so many
strange things when you turn on text grid
and unfortunately at that time when you got
the document mainly from Microsoft
in DOCX format or in DOC format, then
I don't know why that the text illed were
always or not. So... so, we have so many
documents with illed-formatting. So... so,
in 2017, I decided that I want to
test the features romantically by
combining all the settings together, then
and try to fix the those issues as much
as possible.
So like you, we got a problem that an extra cell is
inserted between English and Chinese.
And like extra new line after the numbered list.
And also, some... in some situation, that the characters are close together so that they just looked wrong,
and obviously this is not correct.
So also, I do a side-by-side comparing of Microsoft Office and LibreOffice and try to find those small things.
so I take a piece of a new project. and presented,
I think that, I think in Rome.
So the after I think this I think that
maybe everything is fine for me and I am
not sure what to do next and so in next
year I I try to fix something that is
this kind of picking brought[?] something
rendering[?] so as I saw that Shinji-san,
I think Shinji-san presented that in Rome.
So I... next year, early next year, I just tried to fix that thing.
And also, there is an ongoing there is an ongoing big project for me,
uh...so, forJapanese users that Rubies, the typical use of rubies are, using are, could be above or behind of the base text.
but for traditional Chinese users in Taiwan
that we have... we... when we write in horizontally from left to right, we will mark... the mark... the mark
the Ruby and the right side of the base
text vertically from top to bottom.
So, this is typically used for small
children who is about one first year or
second year in elementary school that they are
learning to write ideographics.
So I did this. I begin to do this at, I think, in 2016.
At that time, I.. my... my daughter is... was
still in kindergarten, then I try to set
the deadline for myself that if I can
make it before she started to learn this
is [?????], but I failed. (laugh)
I missed the deadline, and... but,
anyway I'm happy because I think that if
if you're a teacher or like sometimes
once my... my wife is writing something for
my daughter and then and you... you will
have the only software you can use is
Microsoft Office, so, then, now we have we
finally we have another software that we
can open source software that
we can mark the bottom of in a way that our [????].
So, eventually in 2018, I planned
text layout and Ruby dialog updated
so that there is an option for the vertical write.
And support different kind of file formats.
And also it's actually another bug
that tone... tone mark positioning because
that these symbols are called torn marks
and they have different positioning when
they are writing as tone marks. So... so
I developed those feature, I test with a
special font called a "Bopomofo GPOS Regular" that is designed by But Ko in Taiwan,
and unfortunately, by font is evolving and they
eventually put those [???] for tone mark positioning feature into Source Hans
and something has changed that Sources Hans 2.0.1 does not compatible with LibreOffice. This kind of pity.
So... so, what's next.
So, they are still about 90 issues on the
CJK META list, so there is quite, there is still quite a lot things that we can do.
So, for example, I try to start to work on Ruby in calc early this year.
So the general idea is that we can create character attributes similar to writer,
and then... then we can reuse Asian Phonetic Guide dialogue,
and then we try to import and export from the Excel format,
and then we do the text layout and display,
and then finally we can develop attributes or properties for Open Document Format so that they can be
imported and exported.
Also there are... there are still many things that
ideas that I'm interested like how
to make a Ruby easier to use,
for example, currently split segments for use, so that you can mark
the mark the Ruby text on it, but if we
made mistake then it will be hard to
edit and also for Taiwanese users we
mostly use "mono rubies" for Bopomo.
So, also there are some requests about
improving the tool in general so that it
can be edited more quickly, and search & replace.
And also can Calc and Impress do not support Ruby yet.
So I discussed this with Naru-san,
so he said that Calc is more important
because there... there are some
widespread document there.
So, and also, they are line breaking
rules that I have tried to look into but
I did not have enough time
to handle and they are all have similar
causes and so that might be an
interesting issues to handle in the next research.
Also, vertical writing issues here.
So, for vertical writing, I did not... I did not actually show up anything changed in today's presentation.
I tried, but I cannot do it very well, because, I fixed
it for a few times that approach of you
can't see then and because they will
change to unit unified rendering
software library called HarfBuzz, and, they
broke again and with other developers solved
help as is, here has needs help, that we...
we make it correct again for Linux and
Windows, and for Mac platform it, it is
always incorrect, because I don't
have a Mac, so I cannot even to see I
cannot even see what's the problem
So, in my opinion, although that take unified text layout is correct for horizontal
writing in general, I have no confidence
for the vertical writing, so this might be
one area that were discussing.
So, what's next?
So, if you're still interested
connects[?] then you can come to join us,
join the LibreOffice HackFest tomorrow.
Thank you.